Breaking math news. A large language
model with reasoning capabilities
has solved autonomously a significant puzzle
in mathematics. And of course, did this happen
while I was at home in the office? No. As is
tradition, it happened while I'm trying to be
on vacation. In fact, here's me from a year ago
during a different maths breakthrough complaining
about the fact I was on vacation and pointing out
a year before that the same thing happened. So,
here we are once again. I've taken a break while
I'm down the beach to talk about this breaking
maths news. Although, unlike the last two times
where I was on the west coast of Australia
during spring and then autumn, this time,
this time it's winter. And I've come prepared.
Now, I've actually considered making this
video several times over the past nine months.
But every time I'm like, "Oh, there's not
quite enough for a video." Something else
happens. And now that we are officially
at the point where vibe maths is a thing,
I'm going to have to make the video. So, the
end result is an AI agent has solved a famous
math problem. We'll get to that in a moment. Very
quickly, we're going to zip through the history.
So, the first time I contemplated this video was
back in October of 2025 when a large language
model solved an Erdős problem. But we're going to
have to unpack two things there. First of all, and
this will be fundamental to everything else we're
about to talk about. What is an airish problem?
Paul 'Er-dish', yes, it's pronounced like that,
was a prolific mathematician from the 20th
century. And they've remained incredibly famous
and much loved as a legend among mathematicians.
Check it out. Here's me wearing Erdős' coat. A
long story. But part of why they've remained so
relevant is they generated so many open problems.
There are 1,217 problems documented and cataloged
on the Erdős problem website run by mathematician
Thomas Bloom. And in the 30 years since Erdős'
death, under half of them have been solved. And
famously, Erdős offered prize money for some of
his problems, which now is almost beside the
point. Because these are so famous, if you can
solve one, oh my goodness, it's so prestigious.
And whenever it happens, it's a big deal. So,
it's no surprise these have attracted a lot of AI
attention. And now, what do we mean by solved it?
Well, in this case, Erdős problem 1043, which Paul
Erdős set down in 1958, it was already solved.
So in 2025, what the code did was realize
that the problem was solved in a 1961 paper
which didn't point it out very clearly and in
fact it referenced a solution in a 1959 paper
which was in German. Here's the actual problem.
No need to process this but the gist is let some
function be a monotonic non-constant polynomial
and then assuming that the question is must there
exist a straight line L such the projection
of blah blah blah onto L has measured this
the important bit at most two so that was the
open question here is a 1961 paper that solved
it and it does say it's going to try and get some
you know partial answers to some problems raised
by Erdős however when you get down here this is
the actual solutions See where B is greater than
2.386. That's showing that this is the equivalent
situation. It's definitely greater than two.
In fact, it's greater than 2.386. And nowhere in
here does it mention that Erdős problem. It just
just drops the solution. And in order to do
that, it's using results from this 1959 paper,
which as you can see is in German. and just no
one joined the dots that the machinery in this
paper had been used in a different paper to solve
a problem that it didn't mention and at the time
back in October 25 the incredible mathematician
Terry Tao put a mathstodon post saying how at the
time at least it looked like you know AI wouldn't
be used primarily from applying powerful models
to solve actual problems but rather things like
this like literature reviews locating relevant
prior literature on a given problem particular
particularly as it is down here. If it's, you
know, in scattered literature and there's not a
standardized name for the problem that people use
different names, it can be very hard for humans
to spot those links. So, that's what I thought
the video was going to be about how large language
models are very good search engines and they can
link together bits of research that us humans
with our fleshy brains were unable to connect.
But then things got a bit more complicated
in December of 2025 when Erdős problem 1026
took a different turn. Here is the problem. You've
got a bunch of real numbers x1 all the way up
to xn which are all different. And you want to
work out what the maximum possible sum can be of
okay over all possible monotonic subsequences. And
monotonic just means not changing directions. So
if a number sequence starts going up, it's
got to continue either going up or staying
the same. It can't reverse direction and go down.
And if a sequence is going down, it can't change
and go up. And it was poorly stated originally,
but that's been all cleared up. And it's been
proved. Oh, and his little side character we'll
meet later. Lean. Look at that. Verified in Lean.
Remember that. However, the point here is
this wasn't so much AI solving a problem
as it was helping humans to do that. And
of course, it's Terry Tao again. I'll link
to his blog post below where he talks about
it was combination of existing literature,
online collaboration and AI tools. And in this
case, the AI tools were very much enabling those
first two things. So this was partly really clever
insights from a lot of different mathematicians,
including things like that the problems
equivalent to, you know, uh, packing
different types of squares. And the AI was able
to do deep research searches, sometimes showing
that things didn't exist and in this case finding
a paper from just last year that showed something
that they needed. And so this was the then
stateofthe-art. AI was able to help mathematicians
work a lot faster than they would otherwise. But
AI wasn't coming up with novel proofs on its own
as of the end of 2025. Then in January of this
year, Erdős problem 728 was solved very much more
by AI. Problem 728. Oh, there's our friend
Lean again. Interesting. Now in this case,
we've got two values C and little epsylon. They
need to be sufficiently small. Little ambiguous.
We'll come back to that in a moment. Does that
refer to C or not? And then you got all this
infinity integers blah blah blah such that these
things it's actually a question involving binomial
coefficients and you can see down over here and
we'll start straight away with what Terry's got
to say about it and what's interesting is first of
all AI was used and this was uh deep mind's alpha
proof found trivial solutions basically found that
there were flaws in the statement of the air dish
problem and once they were fixed we could then
get into the AI proof. So actually a was needed
to tidy up the proof in the first place and then
during the solution it was found that that C value
from before it was ambiguous if it was meant to
be small or large and the proof initially thought
it would had to be small turns out it needs to be
large. And if that's all sounding confusing yeah
it is. And there's actually quite a nice blog
post if you want to go into the full details
of what was going on with this proof. But
the short version is it was done by AI.
It involved uh harmonics Aristotle agent which
is a maths theorem solving specific agent that
does a lot of IMO problems and it involved
uh chat GPT as well. So this was a combined
bouncing around proof between chat GPT Aristotle
and putting things into lean and then bouncing it
back through AI to write them up to make them more
legible and add things in. The end result being
here it is a solution to that air dish problem.
And even though it did require a lot of human
handholding, the mathematical insights, the actual
maths was done by AI. A landmark first. [laughter]
Wait. Oh my. Um, okay. I was about to use
the sentence. My thong moved. Uh, flip-flop.
This is what I'm This is what I'm holding up my
chair with. Put that back there. Look, I don't
regret filming outside and um editors love lots
of background white noise and constantly changing
lighting conditions. The point is the point is
life is complicated and things are complicated.
And when I thought I got my head around how sure
large language models are kind of aiding humans
in collaborative mass research and chipping in
new ideas like you know some kind of a kneeling
process just shaking it up as we go along. Then in
April this year 2026, Liam Price, a 23-year-old,
just thought, you know what? I'm going to ask
ChatGpt to solve Erdős problem 1196. And Chat
GPT sat there for like 80 minutes and 17 seconds.
And at the end of it, it spat out a full solution.
And so there you are. We now live
in a world where vibe mathsing
is a thing. Problem 11 196 involves primitive sets
of integers such that blah blah blah blah blah is
another semi-impenetrable math problem. And here's
the paper that solved it. Uh you know classic
maths. So right down the bottom here, page 32, in
the acknowledgements and AI disclosure section, uh
you can see that the initial proof of theorem 1.1
was generated by an autonomous run of GPT 5.4 pro.
And they actually they linked to it here. This
is it. This is what Liam actually put in. Don't
search the internet. This is a test. And then uh
there's the actual problem. Oh, this is latte,
but you know um large language model can can pass
that. No problem. I remember this unconditional
argument may require non-trivial, creative, and
novel elements. And then uh chat replied with,
"Oh yeah, I get what you're doing." And it made it
look a bit nicer. And then it just thought thought
for 80 minutes and 17 seconds and then said,
"Yes." And then said, "In fact, one can prove
something slightly stronger and then spat out
a whole bunch of basically fully formed maths."
In the paper here um they acknowledge that they
took that it was the novel breakthrough done by
chat GPT. Nevertheless, the final proofs in
this paper have been generated and reviewed
by the human authors using the AI generated proofs
as the starting points where appropriate. So the
humans then took the novel mass breakthrough found
by chat GPT and turned it into this uh excellent
mass paper solving that problem. So that's when
I started on this video in earnest to explain
vibe massing and I figured I've just got to draw
a line in the sand if you will and say right this
is where things are at in the middle of 2026. But
the reason I've had to interrupt my vacation and
why this has become breaking mass news is all the
previous problems they weren't like particularly
mathematically interesting. They weren't like
famous problems in that regard, nor were they
easy to state and kind of media friendly. They
were obscure mass problems which yes, it's
interesting that they were solved, but they were
not inherently like big tentpole famous problems.
And now Erdős problem 90 has been solved. The
unit distance problem. The unit distance problem
is reasonably easy to state. Imagine you've got
some number of points on a flat surface, n points,
and you can put them wherever you want. But then
you have a look at all the possible distances
between pairs of points. And you wonder, hang
on, if I could arrange these however I want,
what's the most distances I could get to all
be the same? And because we can scale them,
we call that the unit distance. So the problem is
how do you maximize the number of unit distances
between all the pairs of points on a plane for
any number of n or rather if we were to increase n
crazy numbers of n what would the maximum number
of unit distances look like as that gets bigger
and bigger and laid this out in a paper where he
posed a few other similar problems this is paper
on sets of distances of n points and there's some
other things in here about like the number of
different distances possible for end points. But
what we care about here is function G. So that's
the maximum number of times a given distance R can
occur with end points. And it's called the unit
distance problem because you can scale the whole
thing to make R equal to one. And for some reason
that caught on as the catchy way to describe it.
And down here Erdős proves their value for what
the G function is. So g function always grows
faster than whatever number n is to the power
of all this 1 + c / log of log of n. And then
edish conjectures that it seems likely that g of n
is less than n^ the 1 + epsilon. A quick technical
point here because if you want to look into this
area of maths or a lot of them in the literature,
you'll very quickly come across inequalities
where there's some constant that it seems nobody
cares about. Even in the reporting about this,
you'll see well uh you'll see a C or a delta
both ocean themed puns that it seems nobody cares
about. And that's because what researchers
are really looking at is just the rate at
which these things increase. How fast do they
increase? or more accurately what type of fast.
So in Erdős' original paper his function for the
maximum number of unit distances that he called G
on N he shows that that is greater than N to the
power of 1 + some big C over log of log of N. And
the point is you can make C as big or as small as
you want but you're just diving that up and down.
It's a function as a whole that we care about.
You'll often see this in like big O notation
which I know computer science uses a lot as well.
The point there is just there's some function
to which you can compare the growth of the
function you care about and it doesn't matter if
you scale that other function up and down by some
constant. We're just looking at what is the rate
at which these things are growing. And that's the
big AI breakthrough here. Yeah, it's not like they
found some new arrangement of dots on the plane,
which would be a great visual for which there are
more unit distances than we expect. What they
actually showed is that there definitely exists,
don't know what it is. It's out there somewhere,
some value that they call delta such that
there are infinitely many values of n. Not all
of them, but infinitely many of them for which
there are more uh unit distances the same than n
to the power of 1 plus whatever that delta was.
Yeah. Now that's that's a maths finding. Now
in case you missed that like the first time
I did when I saw the result I thought
that g of n would be less than
growing at the rate of n^ the 1 plus epsilon or
plus delta whereas ai showed the opposite and
this is the paper that came out of it which I find
fascinating about this paper is if you scroll down
it gives you the actual prompt that was there it
is that's what was put into the AI and down here
we have the response that came out of the large
language model and all of this then got tidied up
and put together into a nice neat paper but the
actual insight was done by AI and if we come back
to the actual listing of this problem oh you can
see they're using big O notation not not the C
same thing um there's our friend lean again and
that's partly why large language models are eating
mathematicians lunch first lean is a programming
language that allows you to formalise math proofs
and then verify if they all hold together.
It's a it's a fascinating aspect to formalizing
mathematics and being able to automatically check
if a proof compiles which which I think is amazing
and that's why I think math might be the canary
in the AI mine here because there are things
that large language models are very good at. They
don't have the same bias as humans do in terms of
what the expected result is. Although the training
data obviously brings in human biases. And why the
large language model was so successful in this
case is it was able to pursue lots of different
possible lines of logic all at once. And it could
persist with them further than a human would for
the likelihood of success. And that way it found
a chain of logic which disproved air dish that was
just obscure enough and counterintuitive and not
what we expected that no human had followed that
chain far enough. But a large language model
can do all the chains at once. And why I think
mass is happening first is because of things like
lean. We're able to have AI mark its own homework.
So in other areas AI might produce interesting
results but it could be hallucinating. Whereas
in mathematics we can algorithmically check if the
output is valid or approaching valid. And that way
we can automatically verify and hone the models
in a systematic fashion. And all of that combined
is why a large language model was able to
find a proof no human had. Wow, the winds are
really starting to turn. Oh, more symbolism.
Anyway, uh that's that's the breaking maths
finding. Turns out AI can do maths now. It can
do interesting, [music] significant, famous
mathematics. And I know a lot of AI discussion
like generative AI and all these things where
there's huge ethical questions around where
the training data came from and how it's now
being used to replace people's jobs. That's a
whole thing. I don't want to discredit that. But
it's very interesting that in mathematics because
while you can argue maths is a creative pursuit,
we're also exploring. We're trying to find
things and that's why mathematicians seem to like
using AI. It means they can see further. Now
the big question of should we should we just
dive right in? I don't know. You know, there's a
lot going on. But I will say it's very exciting
that now we can use large language models
to find more interesting mathematics.
Breaking breaking mass news that
literally the day I filmed on the beach,
Google Deep Mind announced they had solved nine
more open airish problems and that was a similar
deal. They're using four different agents that
were able to mark each other's work using lean.
Very clever. We're going to see a lot more of
that. And then archive announced they're going
to ban anyone who uses AI in a paper and leaves
in a mistake, which I think is very clever.
One-year ban. The Liden Declaration on Artificial
Intelligence and Mathematics came out. Definitely
worth a read. Quite interesting. And some
humans have now used the AI found techniques
from the unit distance problem to prove more
things. So, look, a lot's happening. I've
actually waited a little while to upload this in
case there were more. This seems to be a plateau.
So, here you are. This is where we're at in
2026. Who knows where we're going to go next?